<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
	 xml:id="mod.modules"
	 xml:lang="en"
	 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Modules</title>
  <para>A <firstterm>module</firstterm> is <quote>a named group of methods,
  constants, and class variables</quote> <biblioref linkend="bib.flan08"/>. It
  is, therefore, similar to a class except it can neither inherit behaviour nor
  be instantiated. Indeed, <literal>Module</literal> is the superclass of
  <literal>Class</literal>, the latter defining only three additional methods:
  <literal>:new</literal>, <literal>:allocate</literal>, and
  <literal>:superclass</literal>.</para>
  <sect1 xml:id="mod.creation">
    <title>Creation</title>
    <sect2 xml:id="mod.module-keyword">
      <title><literal>module</literal> Keyword</title>
      <!--figure>
        <title>Syntax diagram of the <literal>module</literal> keyword
      </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/module.png" format="PNG" width="4in"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure-->
      <para>The <literal>module <replaceable>name</replaceable>…end</literal>
      expression opens a module named <replaceable>name</replaceable>. If the
      constant <replaceable>name</replaceable> is already defined it must refer
      to an existing module, otherwise a <literal>TypeError</literal> is
      raised.  If <replaceable>name</replaceable> was previously undefined, it
      is created as a <literal>Module</literal> object. That both modules and
      classes are named with constants, means they share the same namespace: a
      given (qualified) constant cannot name a class and a module
      simultaneously. The module body, which may be empty, is the elliptical
      region in the expression. It introduces a new context in which
      <literal>self</literal> refers to the current module.</para>
      <sect3 xml:id="mod.reopening">
        <title>Reopening Modules</title>
        <para>If <literal>module</literal> is used with the name of a pre-existing
        module that module is <emphasis>re-opened</emphasis>. If a method is defined in a
        re-opened module with the same name as a pre-existing method in the
        same module the old method is overwritten with the new.</para>
        <para>Modules can be made immutable, effectively preventing them from
        being reopened by freezing the module object. Frozen modules raise
        <literal>RuntimeError</literal>s when methods are defined, or variables
        manipulated, in their context.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="mod.module-new">
      <title><literal>Module.new</literal></title>
      <para>The <literal>Module.new</literal> constructor can be used to create a new
      anonymous module. It is usually passed a block argument which is
      evaluated in the context of the created module using
      <literal>module_eval</literal>.</para>
      <para><literal>Kernel.load</literal> can<footnote><para>And does, when supplied with a second argument that
      is true, i.e. <literal>load file, true</literal>.
      </para></footnote> use an
      anonymous module to prevent a source file from affecting the global
      namespace. The classes and modules the source file defines are created
      in the context of this anonymous namespace, making them inaccessible to
      the caller. The source file must explicitly specify the constants it
      wishes to share with the caller by assigning them to global variables.</para>
      <para>A module is an object like any other, so by assigning an anonymous
      object to a <link linkend="var.local">local variable</link>, for example, it
      only exists for as long as the variable does, and is invisible from
      disjoint scopes.</para>
      <para>However, magic happens if you assign an anonymous module to a
      constant: the module takes on its name. Specifically, sending
      <literal>:to_s</literal><footnote><para>…or <literal>:inspect</literal>, <literal>:name</literal>, and
      any other method which uses <literal>#to_s</literal> internally.
    </para></footnote> to an anonymous module
      causes a search to be done for the first constant the module was
      assigned to: if one is found, that becomes the module’s name.</para>
      <para>This technique cannot be used to re‐open modules. Assigning an
      anonymous module to a constant naming another module creates a new
      module with the same name, clobbering the old one.</para>
      <example xml:id="ex.module-new">
        <title>Using <literal>Module.new</literal> to create an anonymous
        module
      </title>
        <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/module-new.rb" parse="text"/></programlisting>
      </example>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="mod.mixins">
    <title>Mixins</title>
    <para>The primary use of modules is <firstterm>mixins</firstterm>: imbuing a given
    class with the instance methods, or <firstterm>features</firstterm>, of a given
    module. A class may have any number of modules mixed in.</para>
    <sect2 xml:id="mod.mixin-to-class">
      <title>Mixing a Module into a Class</title>
      <para>Mixing-in a module to a class effectively enables multiple
      inheritance: appending to the class features from any number of
      sources. By contrast, classes may only <link linkend="cla.inheritance">inherit</link> from a maximum of one other
      class.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="mod.mixin-to-module">
      <title>Mixing a Module into a Module</title>
      <para>It is less common to mixin a module to another module, but legal
      nevertheless. The result is simply that the features of the included
      module are copied to the other module.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="mod.inclusion">
      <title>Inclusion</title>
      <para><literal>Module#include</literal> takes one or more module names as
      arguments, then mixes them in to the enclosing class. Contrary to
      intuition, the named modules are mixed-in in the reverse order in
      which they are named. That is, <literal>include A, B</literal> appends the
      features of module <literal>B</literal>, then module <literal>A</literal>.
      Therefore, if <literal>A</literal> and <literal>B</literal> define an instance
      method with the same name, <literal>B</literal>’s copy will be overwritten
      by <literal>A</literal>’s.</para>
      <para>Specifically, when used in the context of a class named
      <replaceable>class</replaceable> <literal>#include</literal> sends each of its arguments
      <literal>:append_features</literal> with <replaceable>class</replaceable> as an argument. The
      default behaviour is defined by <literal>Module#append_features</literal>,
      which adds the named modules to <replaceable>class</replaceable>’s method search path
      then sends the <link linkend="mod.included">:included</link> message to
      each. A corollary is that if a class defines its own
      <literal>#append_features</literal> method, it must call <literal>super</literal> so
      as to invoke <literal>Module#append_features</literal>; otherwise, the module
      is not mixed in.</para>
      <sect3 xml:id="mod.included">
        <title><literal>included</literal> Callback</title>
        <para>When a module has been included in a class it is sent a message
        named <literal>:included</literal>, with the class name as an argument. This
        allows the module to perform initialization such as dynamically adding
        additional methods or variables to the named class. Be aware, however,
        that <literal>:included</literal> is sent <emphasis>every</emphasis> time
        <literal>Module#include</literal> is used, even if the module is already
        included in the class.</para>
        <para><literal>:included</literal> is sent <emphasis>after</emphasis> the module has been
        included, so is powerless to prevent the inclusion or otherwise
        condition it on some prerequisite. Its return value is ignored because
        <literal>Module#include</literal> always returns the class object in which
        it is used.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 xml:id="mod.class-include">
        <title><literal>Class#include?</literal></title>
        <para>The <literal>Class#include?</literal> predicate returns
        <literal>true</literal> if the module given as its argument has been
        mixed-in to the receiver; <literal>false</literal> otherwise.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 xml:id="mod.class-included-modules">
        <title><literal>Class#included_modules</literal></title>
        <para><literal>Class#included_modules</literal> returns an <literal>Array</literal>
        of <literal>Module</literal>s mixed-in to the receiver in the reverse
        order of their inclusion. As <literal>Object</literal> includes the
        <literal>Kernel</literal> module, this method will usually return
        <literal>Kernel</literal> as the last element.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="mod.extension">
      <title>Extension</title>

      <para>Given a list of modules, <literal>Kernel#extend</literal> mixes
      them into to a specific object by <link
      linkend="mod.inclusion">including</link> them in its receiver’s <link
      linkend="cla.singleton">singleton class</link>. Specifically, it sends
      each of its arguments an <literal>:extend_object</literal> message with
      the receiver as an argument. The default behaviour of
      <literal>:extend_object</literal> is provided by
      <literal>Module</literal>, which <link
      linkend="mod.inclusion">includes</link> the module into the receiver’s
      singleton class, then sends the module an <literal>:extended</literal>
      message. As with <literal>Module#append_features</literal>, modules which
      define their own <literal>#extend_object</literal> methods must employ
      <literal>super</literal> to actually effect the extension.</para>

      <example xml:id="ex.extend-class">
        <title>Using <literal>#extend</literal> to mix‐in a class method.
      </title>
        <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/extend-class.rb" parse="text"/></programlisting>
      </example>
      <sect3 xml:id="mod.extend-self">
        <title>Extending <literal>self</literal></title>
        <para>An idiomatic application of <literal>extend</literal> is to use
        <literal>extend self</literal> within the context of a module. The effect
        is to mix the current module into its <link linkend="cla.singleton">singleton class</link>:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><link linkend="met.visibility">Public</link> instance methods can
          be invoked as instance methods in the context of the module,
          i.e. without an explicit receiver, and singleton methods of the
          module from anywhere.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><link linkend="met.visibility">Private and protected</link> instance methods can only be invoked from within the context of the module.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>An example of <literal>extend self</literal> is provided in a
        <link linkend="ex.module-namespacing-extend-self">figure
        below</link>.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="mod.namespacing">
    <title>Namespacing</title>
    <para>Modules can be used for <firstterm>namespacing</firstterm>: to combine a set of
    methods with a common purpose so their names do not clash with unrelated
    methods, and they are able to share data. Classes can be <link linkend="cla.nesting">used in the same way</link>.</para>
    <para>Modules are preferable to classes in this respect when the namespace
    cannot be sensibly instantiated. The use of a module clarifies this aspect
    of the <acronym>API</acronym>.</para>
    <para>Methods are defined in the module’s <link linkend="cla.singleton">singleton class</link>, then invoked with the
    module name as the receiver:
    <literal><replaceable>module</replaceable>.<replaceable>selector</replaceable></literal>.</para>
    <example xml:id="ex.module-namespacing">
      <title>Modules can be used as namespaces by defining methods on
      their singleton class
    </title>
      <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/module-namespacing.rb" parse="text"/></programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>Brown <biblioref begin="133" end="138" linkend="bib.brown09" units="pages"/>
    suggests this technique can be useful in the following circumstances:</para>
    <blockquote>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You are solving a single, atomic task that involves lots of steps
        that would be better broken out into helper functions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>You are wrapping some functions that don’t rely on much common
        state between them, but are related to a common topic.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The code is very general and can be used standalone or the code is
        very specific but doesn’t relate directly to the object that it is
        meant to be used by.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The problem you are solving is small enough where object
        orientation does more to get in the way than it does to help you.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </blockquote>
    <para>This technique can be used in conjunction with <link linkend="mod.extend-self">extend self</link> to create private
    helper methods: accessible to the module methods; inaccessible from
    outside the module.</para>
    <example xml:id="ex.module-namespacing-extend-self">
      <title>A method can be grouped with private helper methods by
      using a module that <literal>extend</literal>s <literal>self</literal></title>
      <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/module-namespacing-extend-self.rb" parse="text"/></programlisting>
    </example>
    <sect2 xml:id="mod.nesting">
      <title>Nesting</title>
      <para>A module may be defined within the body of another class or module.
        The fully qualified name of the inner module is
        <literal><replaceable>outer</replaceable>::<replaceable>inner</replaceable></literal>, i.e. the module names
        are concatenated with the <link linkend="var.constants-references">scope operator</link>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="mod.module-functions">
    <title>Module Functions</title>
    <para>A single module may be used both as a namespace and a mix-in. The
    first case requires the module’s methods to be singleton methods on the
    <literal>Module</literal> object; the second requires them to be instance
    methods.</para>
    <example xml:id="ex.module-namespace-and-mixin">
      <title>The <literal>Math</literal> module can be used as both a
      namespace and a mix-in.
    </title>
      <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/module-namespace-and-mixin.rb" parse="text"/></programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>One solution is <literal>Module#module_function</literal>, which is
    used to convert a mix-in module to a namespace module. In the context of a
    module, <literal>module_function</literal> is provided with one or more
    instance method names as arguments. Alternatively,
    <literal>module_function</literal> may be invoked without arguments, in
    which case it affects all instance methods defined subsequently within the
    same module. In both cases, each affected method is copied to the module’s
    singleton class then the original method is made private. The duplication
    satisfies the requirement that methods are both instance and singleton
    methods. The visibility change forces classes which mix-in the module to
    invoke its methods in the “functional style”, that is without an explicit
    receiver, so as not to confuse them with traditional instance methods
    <biblioref begin="251" end="252" linkend="bib.flan08"/>.</para>
    <example xml:id="ex.module-function">
      <title><literal>module_function</literal> enables a module to be used
      both as a namespace and mix-in
    </title>
      <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/module-function.rb" parse="text"/></programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>A weakness of <literal>module_function</literal> is that it prevents a
    singleton method of the module from calling a private method of the same
    module.</para>
    <example xml:id="ex.module-function-private-method">
      <title><literal>module_function</literal> foils the calling of a
      private instance method from a singleton method
    </title>
      <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/module-function-private-method.rb" parse="text"/></programlisting>
    </example>
    <para><link linkend="mod.extend-self">extend self</link> does not
    exhibit this problem, but neither does it offer the granularity of
    <literal>module_function</literal>—it copies all instance methods into the
    singleton class—nor automatically privatise instance methods.</para>
    <example xml:id="ex.module-function-extend-self">
      <title><literal>extend self</literal> allows the calling of a private
      instance method from a singleton method
    </title>
      <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/module-function-extend-self.rb" parse="text"/></programlisting>
    </example>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="mod.context">
    <title>Context</title>
    <sect2 xml:id="mod.module-eval">
      <title>Module Eval</title>
      <para><literal>Module#module_eval</literal> takes a string or block which it
      evaluates in the receiver’s context, setting <literal>self</literal> to the
      receiver. The evaluated code can access the modules’s state, invoke its
      singleton methods, and define methods.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="mod.module-exec">
      <title>Module Exec</title>
      <para><literal>Module#module_exec</literal> behaves as
      <literal>Module#module_eval</literal> except it requires a block, to which it
      passes any arguments it has received.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
