<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
         xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:lang="en" 
         version="5.0"
         xml:id="pro.programs">
  <title>Programs</title>
  
  <para>Every entity in Ruby is an object. Objects can remember things and communicate with each other by sending and receiving messages <biblioref begin="44" end="44" linkend="bib.goldberg76" units="pages"/>. A Ruby program describes how certain objects must communicate to achieve some definite ends. This chapter provides an overview of the structure and interpretation of Ruby programs.</para>

  <sect1 xml:id="pro.lexical">
    <title>Lexical Structure</title>
    
    <para><firstterm>Tokens</firstterm><footnote><para><literal>Ripper</literal> is a class in the standard library for parsing and analysing Ruby.  The <literal>Ripper.tokenize</literal> method takes a string of code as an argument and returns an array of its constituent tokens.  Experiment with this method in <acronym>IRB</acronym> (<literal>irb -rripper</literal>) to test your assumptions of how tokenization works.</para></footnote> are <quote>the mark or series of marks that denote one symbol or word in the language</quote> <biblioref begin="59" end="62" linkend="bib.fischer92" units="pages"/>. A Ruby program consists of a combination of the following tokens: <link linkend="pro.comments">comments</link>, <link linkend="pro.literals">literals</link>, <link linkend="pun.punctuation">punctuation</link>, <link linkend="pro.identifiers">identifiers</link>, and keywords.</para>

    <sect2 xml:id="pro.comments">
      <title>Comments</title>
      
      <para><firstterm>Comments</firstterm> are remarks which do not affect the meaning of a program. They are introduced with a number sign (<literal>U＋0023</literal>) and continue until the end of the line: the text between <literal>#</literal> and the end of the line is ignored by the interpreter. Comments are not recognised inside of <link linkend="str.strings">string</link>/<link linkend="reg.regexps">regexp</link> literals—they are interpreted literally—however, regexps support an alternative form of embedded comment. There is no specific construct for multiline comments, but they may be approximated with <link linkend="pro.embedded-doc">embedded documentation</link>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="pro.embedded-doc">
      <title>Embedded Documentation</title>
     
      <para><firstterm>Embedded documentation</firstterm> is a portion of a source file that contains documentation intended for a postprocessor such as <literal>rdoc</literal>, and as such is ignored by the interpreter. It is introduced by a line beginning <literal>=begin</literal>, that is an equals sign (<literal>U＋003D</literal>) followed by the string <literal>begin</literal>, and continues until a line beginning <literal>=end</literal> is encountered.</para>
      
      <para>Both <literal>=begin</literal> and <literal>=end</literal> may be followed by arbitrary text, which is included in the embedded documentation, as long as it is preceded by a whitespace character.  Conventionally, the text following <literal>=begin </literal> names the tool for which the documentation is intended.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="pro.whitespace">
      <title>Whitespace</title>
      
      <para><firstterm>Whitespace</firstterm> consists only of <literal>U＋0009</literal>, <literal>U＋000B</literal>–<literal>U＋000D</literal>, and the space character (<literal>U＋0020</literal>), i.e. <acronym>ASCII</acronym> whitespace other than the newline. Its primary role in Ruby syntax is to separate tokens and terminate statements. When whitespace is syntactically significant it is typically collapsed to a single space.  The few areas of syntax where whitespace has different semantics are clearly labeled.</para>

      <para>Newlines may function as whitespace, too, depending on the context in which they are used. See the <link linkend="pro.statement-terminators"/> for further details.</para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 xml:id="pro.literals">
      <title>Literals</title>
      
      <para>An <firstterm>object literal</firstterm> is a syntactical shortcut for the instantiation of a particular core object. Literals exist for strings, numbers, symbols, arrays, hashes, ranges, lambdas.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="pro.identifiers">
      <title>Identifiers</title>
      
      <para>An <firstterm>identifier</firstterm> is the name of a <link linkend="var.variables">variable</link> or <link linkend="met.methods">method</link>. It must not contain any <acronym>US</acronym>-<acronym>ASCII</acronym> character other than the alphanumerics (A—Z, a—z, 0–9) and the low line (<literal>U＋005F</literal>), or begin with a <acronym>US</acronym>-<acronym>ASCII</acronym> digit. However, it may contain any other character legal in the <link linkend="enc.source">source encoding</link>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="pro.syntax">
    <title>Syntactical Structure</title>
    
    <sect2 xml:id="pro.expressions">
      <title>Expressions</title>
      
      <para>An <firstterm>expression</firstterm><footnote><para>We follow the lead of Aho, Sethi, &amp; Ullman in defining <emphasis>expression</emphasis> by recursion rather than direct description <biblioref linkend="bib.aho86"/>.</para></footnote> is a syntactical construct that produces a value. Since every entity is an object, every expression evaluates to an object. It is either primary or compound.</para><para><firstterm>Primary expressions</firstterm> comprise atomic<footnote><para>As Turbak, Gifford, &amp; Sheldon note, this characterisation is patently false even for toy languages since, in their example, <quote>numerals can be broken down into digits</quote>, however we, too, will <quote>ignore this detail</quote> <biblioref begin="20" end="22" linkend="bib.turbak08" units="pages"/>.</para></footnote> units such as <link linkend="var.variables">variable references</link> and numeric, <link linkend="str.literals">string</link><footnote><para>Double‐quoted strings that interpolate other expressions are compound expressions.</para></footnote>, and symbol, <link linkend="reg.literals">regexp</link><footnote><para>Regexps that interpolate other expressions are also compound expressions.</para></footnote>, and <link linkend="pro.keyword-literals">keyword</link>, literals.</para>
	
      <sect3 xml:id="pro.operators">
	<title>Operators</title>

	<para>Primary expressions can be combined with <firstterm>operators</firstterm> to produce <firstterm>compound expressions</firstterm>. An operator is a token with <firstterm>precedence</firstterm>, <firstterm>associativity</firstterm>, and <firstterm>arity</firstterm>, which operates upon one or more values (termed its <firstterm>operands</firstterm>).</para>

	<para>Precedence dictates which of two different operations should be carried out first. It can be overridden by grouping sub-expressions that should be performed earlier with parentheses. When parenthetical groups contain other parenthetical groups, the innermost is given the highest precedence.</para>

	<para>If both operators have the same precedence, the tie is broken by considering their associativity: left-associative expressions are evaluated left to right; right-associative expressions are evaluated right to left. If two operators have the same precedence and are both non-associative, they cannot be used in the same expression without parenthesising one or both.</para>

	<para>An operator’s arity is the number of arguments it takes. An arity of 1 makes an operator <firstterm>unary</firstterm>, 2,	<firstterm>binary</firstterm>, and 3, <firstterm>ternary</firstterm>.</para>
	
	<table rules="groups">
	  <caption>Operators in descdending order of precedence</caption>

	  <thead>
	    <tr>
	      <th>Operators</th>
	      <th>Arity</th>
	      <th>Associativity</th>
	      <th>Function</th>
	    </tr>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>!</literal>, <literal>~</literal>, <literal>+</literal></td>
	      <td>Unary</td>
	      <td>Right</td>
	      <td>NOT, bitwise complement, unary plus.</td> 
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>**</literal></td>
	      <td>Binary</td>
	      <td>Right</td>
	      <td>Exponentiation</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>-</literal></td>
	      <td>Unary</td>
	      <td>Right</td>
	      <td>Unary minus.</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>*</literal>, <literal>/</literal>, <literal>%</literal></td>
	      <td>Binary</td>
	      <td>Left</td>
	      <td>Multiplication, division, modulus.</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>+</literal>, <literal>-</literal></td>
	      <td>Binary</td>
	      <td>Left</td>
	      <td>Addition, subtraction.</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>&lt;&lt;</literal>, <literal>&gt;&gt;</literal></td>
	      <td>Binary</td>
	      <td>Left</td>
	      <td>Left-shift or append, right-shift.</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>&amp;</literal></td>
	      <td>Binary</td>
	      <td>Left</td>
	      <td>Bitwise AND.</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>|</literal>, <literal>^</literal></td>
	      <td>Binary</td>
	      <td>Left</td>
	      <td>Bitwise OR, Bitwise XOR.</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>&lt;</literal>, <literal>&lt;=</literal>, <literal>&gt;=</literal>, <literal>&gt;</literal></td>
	      <td>Binary</td>
	      <td>Left</td>
	      <td>Inequalities.</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>==</literal>, <literal>===</literal>,
	      <literal>!=</literal>, <literal>=~</literal>,
	      <literal>=~</literal>, <literal>!~</literal>,
	      <literal>&lt;=&gt;</literal></td>
	      <td>Binary</td>
	      <td>None</td>
	      <td>Equality and comparison.</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>&amp;&amp;</literal></td>
	      <td>Binary</td>
	      <td>Left</td>
	      <td>AND</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>||</literal></td>
	      <td>Binary</td>
	      <td>Left</td>
	      <td>OR</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>..</literal>, <literal>...</literal></td>
	      <td>Binary</td>
	      <td>None</td>
	      <td><literal>Range</literal> constructor.</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td>…<literal>?</literal>…<literal>:</literal>…</td>
	      <td>Ternary</td>
	      <td>Right</td>
	      <td>Conditional</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>rescue</literal></td>
	      <td>Binary</td>
	      <td>Left</td>
	      <td>Exception handling.</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>=</literal></td>
	      <td>Binary</td>
	      <td>Right</td>
	      <td>Assignment.</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>**=</literal>, <literal>*=</literal>, <literal>/=</literal>, <literal>%=</literal>, <literal>+=</literal>, <literal>-=</literal>, <literal>&lt;&lt;=</literal>, <literal>&gt;&gt;=</literal>, <literal>&amp;&amp;=</literal>, <literal>&amp;=</literal>, <literal>||=</literal>, <literal>|=</literal>, <literal>^=</literal></td> 
	      <td>Binary</td>
	      <td>Right</td>
	      <td>Abbreviated assignment.</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>defined?</literal></td>
	      <td>Unary</td>
	      <td>None</td>
	      <td>Variable tests.</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>not</literal></td>
	      <td>Unary</td>
	      <td>Right</td>
	      <td>NOT</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>and</literal>, <literal>or</literal></td>
	      <td>Binary</td>
	      <td>Left</td>
	      <td>AND, OR</td>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	      <td><literal>if</literal>, <literal>unless</literal>, <literal>while</literal>, <literal>until</literal></td>
	      <td>Binary</td>
	      <td>None</td>
	      <td>Statement modifiers.</td>
	    </tr>
	  </tbody>
	</table>
      </sect3>
      
      <sect3 xml:id="pro.keyword-literals">
        <title>Keyword Literals</title>
        
        <sect4 xml:id="pro.true">
          <title><literal>true</literal></title>
          
          <para>The <literal>true</literal> keyword returns the singleton instance of <literal>TrueClass</literal>. Its value is, by definition, true.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 xml:id="pro.false">
          <title><literal>false</literal></title>

          <para>The <literal>false</literal> keyword returns the singleton instance of <literal>FalseClass</literal>. Its value is, by definition, false.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 xml:id="pro.nil">
          <title><literal>nil</literal></title>

          <para>The <literal>nil</literal> keyword returns the singleton instance of <literal>NilClass</literal>. Its value is represents the absence of a value. The <literal>Kernel.nil?</literal> predicate returns <literal>true</literal> if its value is <literal>nil</literal>; <literal>false</literal> otherwise.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 xml:id="pro.self">

          <title><literal>self</literal></title>

          <para><literal>self</literal> always evaluates to the current object. Outside of any class definition, i.e. at the top‐level, the current object is an instance of <literal>Object</literal> called <literal>main</literal>. Inside a class definition, but outside of a method definition, the current object is an instance of <literal>Class</literal>. Within a method definition the current object is the instance of the containing class.</para>

          <example xml:id="ex.self-as-the-implicit-receiver">
            <title><literal>self</literal> is always defined; its value depends on the enclosing context.</title>

            <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/self-as-the-implicit-receiver.rb" parse="text"/></programlisting>
          </example>
        </sect4>
        
        <sect4 xml:id="pro.file">
          <title><literal>__FILE__</literal> / <literal>__LINE__</literal></title>

	  <para>See <xref linkend="pro.tracing"/>.</para>          
        </sect4>
        
        <sect4 xml:id="pro.encoding">
          <title><literal>__ENCODING__</literal></title>

          <para>Evaluates to an <literal>Encoding</literal> object representing the current source encoding, i.e. that of <link linkend="pro.file">__FILE__</link>.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="pro.statements">
      <title>Statements</title>
      
      <para>A statement is an expression whose value is ignored<footnote><para>Turbak, Gifford, &amp; Sheldon offer a further example of distinguishing between statements and expressions by considering their context <biblioref begin="472" end="476" linkend="bib.turbak08" units="pages"/>.</para></footnote>. In practice, this implies that a statement is executed for its side-effects, because an expression executed for neither its value nor effect is semantically meaningless.</para>

      <sect3 xml:id="pro.statement-terminators">
        <title>Statement Terminators &amp; Newlines</title>
        
        <para>One statement must be separated from the next by a statement terminator. This may be a semicolon (<literal>U＋003B</literal>) or newline. The latter is preferred because it leads to a natural separation: each statement on its own line. However, a newline does not terminate a statement if:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>It is immediately preceded by a reverse solidus (<literal>U＋005C</literal>).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>It is preceded by an <link linkend="mes.operators">operator</link>, with optional intervening <link linkend="pro.whitespace">whitespace</link>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>It is immediately preceded by a comma (<literal>U＋002C</literal>) or full stop (<literal>U＋002E</literal>) in a <link linkend="mes.expressions">message expression</link> or <link linkend="arr.arrays">array</link>/<link linkend="has.hashes">hash</link> literal, with optional intervening whitespace.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>It is preceded by a left parenthesis, curly bracket, or square bracket, with optional intervening whitespace. (Allows the argument list of <link linkend="mes.expressions">message expressions</link>, and <link linkend="arr.arrays">array</link> or <link linkend="has.hashes">hash</link> literals to span multiple lines).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The first non-whitespace character on the following line is a full stop (<literal>U＋002E</literal>). (Allows <link linkend="mes.chaining">chained</link> message expressions to span lines).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>It is preceded by one of the following keywords: <literal>alias</literal>, <literal>and</literal>, <literal>begin</literal>, <literal>def</literal>, <literal>defined?</literal>, <literal>case</literal>, <literal>class</literal>, <literal>else</literal>, <literal>elsif</literal>, <literal>ensure</literal>, <literal>for</literal>, <literal>if</literal>, <literal>in</literal>, <literal>module</literal>, <literal>not</literal>, <literal>or</literal>, <literal>then</literal>, <literal>undef</literal>, <literal>unless</literal>, <literal>until</literal>, <literal>when</literal>, or <literal>while</literal>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="pro.data">
      <title><literal>__END__</literal></title>
      
      <para>If the interpreter encounters a line consisting solely of the token <literal>__END__</literal>, it ignores any lines that follow. However, they are made available to the program via a global, read-only <link linkend="io.io"><literal>IO</literal></link> object named <literal>DATA</literal>.</para>

      <example xml:id="ex.__end__">
	<title>Lines following <literal>__END__</literal> can be read via the <literal>IO</literal> object <literal>DATA</literal>.</title>

	<programlisting><xi:include href="examples/__end__.rb" parse="text"/></programlisting>
      </example>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="pro.interpretation">
    <title>Interpretation</title>
    

    <sect2 xml:id="pro.interpreter">
      <title>Interpreter</title>

      <para>The statements and expressions that comprise a program are collectively known as its <firstterm>source code</firstterm>. To execute a program its source code must be provided to a Ruby <firstterm>interpreter</firstterm>: the program that executes Ruby source code. The reference implementation<footnote><para>There are several excellent alternative implementations such as <link xlink:href="http://jruby.org/">JRuby</link> and <link xlink:href="http://rubini.us/">Rubinius</link>. However, for the purposes of this book neither are recommended because, although JRuby is close, they are not yet compatible with Ruby 1.9.</para></footnote> of Ruby, or <acronym>MRI</acronym>, contains an interpreter called <command>ruby</command>, so when we speak of <emphasis>executing the interpreter</emphasis> we are referring to running this program.</para>

      <para>The <command>ruby</command> program is invoked as <literal>ruby <replaceable>options</replaceable> <replaceable>file</replaceable> <replaceable>arguments</replaceable></literal>, all of which are optional. If the <envar>RUBYOPT</envar> environment variable includes the <option>-W</option>, <option>-w</option>, <option>-v</option>, <option>-d</option>, <option>-I</option>, <option>-r</option>, and <option>-K</option> options, they are treated as if they were specified on the command line.</para>

      <para><replaceable>options</replaceable> is zero or more of the options tabulated below. They are passed to the interpreter. If the <option>-e</option> option is given, its argument is the Ruby code to execute. If <replaceable>file</replaceable> is given and it’s the name of a file containing Ruby code, the file is executed. If <replaceable>file</replaceable> is <literal>-</literal> or omitted, the Ruby code to execute is read from standard input. If <replaceable>arguments</replaceable> are given, they are passed to the Ruby program as elements of <literal>ARGV</literal>.</para>

      <informaltable>
	<thead>
	  <tr>
	    <th>Option</th>
	    <th>Description</th>
	  </tr>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-0<replaceable>n</replaceable></option></td>
	    <td>Set the record separator to the character with ASCII code <replaceable>n</replaceable>, which is interpreted as up to three octal digits. If <replaceable>n</replaceable> is omitted, it is 0; if <replaceable>n</replaceable> explicitly specified as <literal>0</literal>, the record separator is <literal>"\n\n"</literal>; if <replaceable>n</replaceable> is <literal>777</literal>, the record separator is <literal>nil</literal>.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-a</option></td>
	    <td>Auto-split mode: when used in conjunction with <option>-n</option> or <option>-p</option>, places <literal>$F = $_.split</literal> at the beginning of the loop body.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-C <replaceable>directory</replaceable></option> / <option>-X <replaceable>directory</replaceable></option></td>
	    <td>Change to the directory named <replaceable>directory</replaceable> before executing the program.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-c</option></td>
	    <td>Check syntax without executing the program: prints an error message if there are syntax errors; prints nothing if there aren’t.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>--copyright</option></td>
	    <td>Display the copyright notice then exits.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-d</option> / <option>--debug</option></td>
	    <td>Assign <literal>true</literal> to <literal>$DEBUG</literal> and <literal>$VERBOSE</literal>, which enables warnings.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>--disable-gems</option></td>
	    <td>Don’t load <emphasis>rubygems</emphasis> implicitly or add gem directories to the load path.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-E <replaceable>encoding</replaceable></option> / <option>--encoding <replaceable>encoding</replaceable></option></td>
	    <td>Set the default encoding. If <replaceable>encoding</replaceable> is a single encoding name, it is the default external encoding; if it is two encoding names separated by colons, the first encoding is the default external, and the second, the default internal.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-e <replaceable>string</replaceable></option></td>
	    <td>Execute <replaceable>string</replaceable> as Ruby code. If this option is given multiple times, its arguments form successive lines of the same program.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-F <replaceable>sep</replaceable></option></td>
	    <td>Set the input field separator (<literal>$;</literal>) to <replaceable>sep</replaceable>, where <replaceable>sep</replaceable> is a single character or regular expression without the <literal>/…/</literal> delimiters.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-h</option> / <option>--help</option></td>
	    <td>Display usage help then exit.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-I <replaceable>directories</replaceable></option></td>
	    <td>Prepend <replaceable>directories</replaceable> to <literal>$LOAD_PATH</literal>. If <replaceable>directories</replaceable> contains multiple directories, they are separated by a colon on Unix-like systems; a semicolon on Windows systems. May be given multiple times.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-i <replaceable>extension</replaceable></option></td>
	    <td>For each file named in <literal>ARGV</literal>, data written to the standard output stream will be written to that file. If <replaceable>extension</replaceable> is given, then before a file, <replaceable>file</replaceable>, is modified it is copied to <literal><replaceable>file</replaceable><replaceable>extension</replaceable></literal>.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-K<replaceable>code</replaceable></option></td>
	    <td>Set the default external encoding and source encoding to <emphasis>US-ASCII</emphasis> if <replaceable>code</replaceable> is <literal>a</literal>, <literal>A</literal>, <literal>n</literal>, or <literal>N</literal>; <emphasis>UTF-8</emphasis> if <replaceable>code</replaceable> is <literal>u</literal> or <literal>U</literal>; <emphasis>Shift-JIS</emphasis> is <replaceable>code</replaceable> is <literal>s</literal> or <literal>S</literal>; or <emphasis>EUC-JP</emphasis> if <literal>code</literal> is <literal>e</literal> or <literal>E</literal>.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-l</option></td>
	    <td>Set <literal>$\</literal> to <literal>$/</literal> and remove <literal>$/</literal> from the end of input lines.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-n</option></td>
	    <td>Assume a <literal>while gets; … ; end</literal> loop around the Ruby program.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-p</option></td>
	    <td>Assume a <literal>while gets; … ; print; end</literal> loop around the Ruby program.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-r<replaceable>library</replaceable></option></td>
	    <td>Require the library or gem named <replaceable>library</replaceable> before executing the program.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-S</option></td>
	    <td>Try to locate the specified program file relative to the <envar>RUBYPATH</envar> or <envar>PATH</envar> environment variables, before locating it normally.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-s</option></td>
	    <td>Remove any options following the program filename from <literal>ARGV</literal>, then create a global variable named after the option and assign to it the option’s value. Options without values are assumed to be <literal>true</literal>.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-T<replaceable>level</replaceable></option></td>
	    <td>Set the safe level to <replaceable>level</replaceable>, or <literal>1</literal> if <replaceable>level</replaceable> is omitted.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-U</option></td>
	    <td>Set the default internal encoding to UTF-8.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-v</option> / <option>--verbose</option></td>
	    <td>Enable warnings by setting <literal>$VERBOSE</literal> to <literal>true</literal>, then print the interpreter version number. If a program is specified, execute it.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>--version</option></td>
	    <td>Display the interpreter version number then exits.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-w</option></td>
	    <td>Enable warnings by setting <literal>$VERBOSE</literal> to <literal>true</literal>, then execute the named program—if given—or read the program from standard input.</td> 
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-W<replaceable>level</replaceable></option></td>
	    <td>Set the warning level to <replaceable>level</replaceable>: silence all warnings if <replaceable>level</replaceable> is <literal>0</literal>; use standard warning level if <replaceable>level</replaceable> is <literal>1</literal>; otherwise, or if <replaceable>level</replaceable> is omitted, equivalent to <option>-w</option>.</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td><option>-x <replaceable>directory</replaceable></option></td>
	    <td>Strip each line of the program file that precede a line beginning <literal>#!ruby</literal>, change to the directory named <replaceable>directory</replaceable>—if given—then execute the program.</td>
	  </tr>
	</tbody>
      </informaltable>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="pro.source-files">
      <title>Source Files</title>
      
      <para>Ruby programs are typically stored in plain text files with an <literal>.rb</literal> filename extension. As explained above, they are typically executed by supplying their filenames as arguments to the <command>ruby</command> interpreter, e.g. <literal>ruby myfile.rb</literal> would execute the source code saved in <literal>myfile.rb</literal>.</para>
    
      <sect3 xml:id="pro.shebang">
        <title>Shebang</title>
        
        <para>The <firstterm>shebang</firstterm><footnote><para>A portmanteau of <emphasis>sharp</emphasis> and <emphasis>bang</emphasis> <biblioref begin="1001" end="1001" linkend="bib.wall00" units="pages"/>, colloquial terms for the number sign (<literal>U＋0023</literal>) and the exclamation mark (<literal>U＋0021</literal>), respectively.</para></footnote> is a notation for informing a UNIX-like operating system of the interpreter with which a script should be executed. If present it must appear as the first line of a source file. It begins with a number sign (<literal>U＋0023</literal>) making it a legal comment line, therefore ignored by the interpreter, which is followed by an exclamation mark (<literal>U＋0021</literal>) then the path to the interpreter.</para>

        <para>A typical shebang is <literal>#!/usr/bin/env ruby</literal> which uses <command>env</command> to avoid hardcoding the path to the interpreter.</para>
        
        <para>If a script containing a shebang is executable, it may be executed by entering its filename in the shell. This allows the interpreter to be invoked implicitly, and is a common approach.</para>

	<example xml:id="ex.shebang">
	  <title>A shebang allows Ruby source files to be executed from the shell like a system command</title>

	  <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/shebang.rb" parse="text"/></programlisting>
	</example>

	<example xml:id="ex.shebang-shell">
	  <title>Executing a file with a shebang</title>

	  <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/shebang-shell.txt" parse="text"/></programlisting>
	</example>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 xml:id="pro.source-encoding">
        <title>Source Encoding</title>
        
        <para>Source files are assumed to only contain <acronym>US</acronym>-<acronym>ASCII</acronym> characters, unless they have been explicitly declared to have a different encoding. This topic is explained fully in <link linkend="enc.source"/>.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 xml:id="pro.warnings">
        <title>Warnings</title>
        
        <para><firstterm>Warnings</firstterm>— notices of deprecated, ambiguous, or otherwise problematic, code— are enabled when the interpreter is given the <option>-w</option> switch, e.g. <literal>ruby -w myfile.rb</literal>. For example, Ruby warns when a <link linkend="var.constants">constant</link> that has already been defined is assigned to.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 xml:id="pro.loading-features">
	<title>Loading Features</title>

	<para>A Ruby program may be entirely self-contained, in which case all the code it needs is stored in a single source file. Larger programs, however, are often partitioned such that each major component is stored in a separate file. Additionally, programs often reuse existing code written by third parties. <remark>Introduce Gems here?</remark> In both cases, the program must load and execute these external files, which are collectively termed <firstterm>features</firstterm>.</para>

	<para>A feature must be resolved to a filename: If it begins with <literal>/</literal> it is already an absolute filename; <literal>../</literal>, it is resolved relative to the current working directory; <literal>~/</literal>,  it is resolved relative to the user’s home directory; otherwise, it is resolved relative to a directory in the <firstterm>load path</firstterm>. The load path is an <literal>Array</literal>—named <literal>$LOAD_PATH</literal> or <literal>$:</literal>—of directories searched for a given feature. It is initialised by the interpreter, and modified with the <literal>-I</literal> option or by manipulating <literal>$LOAD_PATH</literal> directly.</para>

      <sect4 xml:id="pro.require">
        <title><literal>require</literal></title>
	
        <para><function>Kernel.require(<replaceable>feature</replaceable>)</function> attempts to load and execute <replaceable>feature</replaceable>. <replaceable>feature</replaceable> is a <literal>String</literal> that can be resolved to the name of an file with a supported extension: either <literal>.rb</literal>—implying it contains Ruby source code—or one of the system’s shared library extensions—implying it is a binary extension.</para>

	<para><replaceable>feature</replaceable> is resolved as explained above. This is repeated for each supported extension by first appending the extension to <replaceable>feature</replaceable>. Finally, <replaceable>feature</replaceable> is searched for in the <firstterm>Gem path</firstterm><footnote><para>This is returned by <literal>gem environment gempath</literal>. Each directory in this path, has its <literal>/gems/</literal> sub-directory searched by appending <literal>/lib/<replaceable>feature</replaceable></literal> to its name. If unsuccessful, it is repeated after having appended each supported extension—<literal>.rb</literal> first—to <replaceable>feature</replaceable>.</para></footnote>. When an existing filename is found, the remaining steps are skipped; if all fail, a <literal>LoadError</literal> is raised.</para>

	<para>If the filename appears in an <literal>Array</literal> named <literal>$LOADED_FEATURES</literal>—alias: <literal>$"</literal>—it has already been required so <function>require</function> returns <literal>false</literal>; otherwise, the filename is loaded with <function>Kernel.load</function> at a safe level of <literal>0</literal>. If the filename was loaded successfully, it is appended to <literal>$LOADED_FEATURES</literal> and <literal>true</literal> is returned.</para>
      </sect4>

      <sect4 xml:id="pro.require_relative">
	<title><literal>require_relative</literal></title>

	<para><function>Kernel.require_relative</function> behaves like <function>require</function>, except it resolves the feature name relative to the file in which it is contained. <function>require_relative <replaceable>path</replaceable></function> is equivalent to <function>require File.expand_path(File.dirname(__FILE__)) + <replaceable>path</replaceable></function>.</para>
      </sect4>

      <sect4 xml:id="pro.load">
        <title><literal>load</literal></title>
	
	<para><function>Kernel.load(<replaceable>feature</replaceable>)</function> resolves <replaceable>feature</replaceable> to a filename, which it then executes. Unlike <replaceable>require</replaceable>, <replaceable>feature</replaceable> can’t omit the filename extension, must contain Ruby source code, is not searched for in the Gem path, is loaded even if appearing in <literal>$LOADED_FEATURES</literal>, and is loaded at the current safe level.</para>

  <para>Once a file is loaded, its constants—therefore class and module definitions—method definitions, and global-, class-, and instance variables are imported into the loading environment. If the optional second parameter is <literal>true</literal>, the file is loaded into an anonymous module, to avoid polluting the caller’s environment.</para>
	
	<para>For example, consider a file, <filename>a.rb</filename>, that comprised the statement <literal>@ivar = :i</literal>. Located in the same directory is the following file:</para>

	<example xml:id="ex.load">
	  <title>Loading and executing an external file</title>

	  <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/load.rb" parse="text"/></programlisting>
	</example>
      </sect4>
    </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="pro.irb">
      <title>IRB</title>
    
      <para>Ruby is distributed with a program called <command>irb</command> which provides an interactive shell, or read‐eval‐print loop, for the interpreter. <acronym>IRB</acronym> works as follows:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You enter a statement of Ruby and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>That statement is evaluated and its value printed to the screen.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>You go back to step 1.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      
      <para>This provides a superb environment for learning Ruby. As you read this book you can enter the examples in IRB and see for yourself how they work.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="pro.eval">
      <title>Evaluating Strings</title>
    
      <para>Source code can be provided as an command-line argument to the interpreter if it is invoked with the <option>-e</option> switch, e.g. <literal>ruby -e 'puts 1 + 2'</literal> executes the code fragment and displays <computeroutput>3</computeroutput>.</para>

      <para>The <literal>Kernel.eval</literal> method provides similar functionality from within a program. Pass it an arbitrary string of source code as an argument and it will return the result. Continuing with the above example, <literal>eval 'puts 1 + 2'</literal>, has the same result.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="pro.tracing">
    <title>Tracing</title>

    <para>Although Ruby does not include a debugger, she offers a variety of features to aid debugging. The keyword <literal>__FILE__</literal> evaluates to a <literal>String</literal> naming the source file currently being executed. The strings <computeroutput>(eval)</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>(irb)</computeroutput> are returned when in an <literal>eval</literal> context and <acronym>IRB</acronym> session, respectively. The keyword <literal>__LINE__</literal> evaluates to a <literal>Fixnum</literal> specifying the line number in the current <literal>__FILE__</literal> being executed. Taken together, thee keywords can be used to produce error messages and warnings that identify the errant code. Indeed, <function>Kernel.eval</function>, <function>Object.instance_eval</function>, and <function>Module.class_eval</function>, accept a filename and line number as their final two arguments, which they use when reporting errors: by using <literal>__FILE__</literal> and <literal>__LINE__</literal> as these values, it becomes easier to trace dynamically generated code.</para>

    <para>Similarly, <function>Kernel.__method__</function>, and its alias: <function>Kernel.__callee__</function>, return the name of the current method as a <literal>Symbol</literal>. If the current method was invoked via an alias, its original name is returned.</para>

    <para><function>Kernel.caller</function> returns a stack trace that culminates with the method that invoked the current method. The <literal>Array</literal> returned has one element per stack frame, organised in reverse chronological order. Each frame is represented as a <literal>String</literal>, which usually includes the filename, line number, and method name. If <function>caller</function> is given an argument, it specifies how many frames to drop from the beginning.</para>

    <para>If a global constant named <literal>SCRIPT_LINES__</literal> is assigned a <literal>Hash</literal>, <function>Kernel.require</function>, <function>Kernel.require_relative</function>, and <function>Kernel.load</function>, append an entry to it for each file they load. The key is the filename as a <literal>String</literal>, and the value is that file’s contents, also as a <literal>String</literal>.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
