<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.0" 
         xml:id="ran.ranges" 
         xml:lang="en">
  
  <title>Ranges</title>
  
  <para>A <literal>Range</literal> represents an immutable sequence between two given values.  It is either <emphasis>inclusive</emphasis> or <emphasis>exclusive</emphasis>: the former includes the endpoint; the latter does not. For example, 0–9 is a range consisting of all single-digit integers, expressed by specifying the start-point and endpoint.</para>
    
    <para>A <literal>Range</literal> literal consists of two values separated by two or three full stops<footnote><para >In the conditional of a branching or looping statement, two or three consecutive full stops don’t create a range; they constitute a <link linkend="flo.flip-flop">Boolean flip-flop</link>.</para></footnote>: the former range is inclusive; the latter exclusive.  For example, <literal>'a'...'z'</literal> represents letters <emphasis>a</emphasis>–<emphasis>y</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>The start-point and endpoint must be comparable with <literal>#&lt;=&gt;</literal>. That is, for a range <literal><replaceable>start</replaceable>..<replaceable>end</replaceable></literal>, <literal><replaceable>start</replaceable> &lt;=&gt; <replaceable>end</replaceable></literal> must return -1, 0, or 1.  <literal>Range#include?(<replaceable>object</replaceable>)</literal> allows ranges to be used as intervals: returning <literal>true</literal> if <replaceable>object</replaceable> is a member; <literal>false</literal> otherwise.</para>

    <para>A range is <firstterm>discrete</firstterm> if it begins with a value that responds to <literal>#succ</literal> by returning the next element of the sequence. It is so called because it represents a finite set of values that can be iterated over with <literal>Range#each</literal>.  Alternatively, <literal>Range#step(<replaceable>n</replaceable>) {|<replaceable>el</replaceable>| }</literal> passes each <replaceable>n</replaceable><superscript>th</superscript> element to the block.</para> <para>A non-discrete range is <firstterm>continuous</firstterm>.  It represents an infinite set of values, therefore a <literal>TypeError</literal> is raised when attempting to iterate over it.</para>
</chapter>
